[
  {
    "id": 1,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The most appropriate site of Haemopoiesis in a twenty-year-old man is the:",
    "options": [
      "Red of the spleen",
      "Liver",
      "Kidney",
      "Thymus",
      "Marrow of the skull, sternum, and iliac crest"
    ],
    "answer": ["Marrow of the skull, sternum, and iliac crest"],
    "explanation": "Hemopoiesis primarily occurs in the bone marrow of certain bones in adults.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 2,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Thrombopoietin is the growth factor for",
    "options": [
      "Erythropoiesis",
      "Granulopoiesis",
      "Megakaryopoiesis",
      "Lymphopoiesis",
      "Monocyte production"
    ],
    "answer": ["Megakaryopoiesis"],
    "explanation": "Thrombopoietin is the primary growth factor for the production of platelets (thrombocytes), which are derived from megakaryocytes.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 3,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Which of the following is a B lymphocyte growth factor:",
    "options": ["CFU-GEMM", "CFU-GM", "Interleukin-7", "CFU-Meg", "CFU-BL"],
    "answer": ["Interleukin-7"],
    "explanation": "Interleukin-7 is a cytokine that plays a critical role in the development and survival of B lymphocytes (B cells).",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Immunology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 4,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The extracellular matrix of the bone marrow supports haemopoiesis and consists of the glycoproteins except:",
    "options": [
      "Fibronectin",
      "Haemonectin",
      "Macrophages",
      "Collagen",
      "Proteoglycans"
    ],
    "answer": ["Haemonectin"],
    "explanation": "The bone marrow's extracellular matrix provides structural support for hematopoiesis and consists of various components, including fibronectin, collagen, and proteoglycans. Macrophages are immune cells found within the marrow but are not glycoproteins in the extracellular matrix.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 5,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Components of the red cell membrane",
    "options": [
      "20% carbohydrate",
      "10% phospholipids",
      "20% cholesterol molecules",
      "10% is carbohydrate",
      "None of the above is correct"
    ],
    "answer": ["None of the above is correct"],
    "explanation": "The composition of the red cell membrane includes approximately 52% protein, 40% lipid (mostly phospholipids), and a small amount of carbohydrate. None of the provided options accurately represents the composition.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 6,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Hereditary Spherocytosis",
    "options": [
      "Inheritance is autosomal recessive",
      "Defects proteins in horizontal lattice",
      "Top of defect includes both ankyrin and spectrin deficiency",
      "Aplastic crises does not occur",
      "Diagnosis is normally made from bone marrow film"
    ],
    "answer": ["Top of defect includes both ankyrin and spectrin deficiency"],
    "explanation": "Hereditary spherocytosis is an autosomal dominant disorder characterized by a defect in membrane proteins, including ankyrin and spectrin. This leads to spherically shaped red blood cells, which are less flexible and more prone to hemolysis.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 7,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The following are features of severe Hereditary Spherocytosis:",
    "options": [
      "Gallstones never occur",
      "The hemoglobin level is less than 6g/dl",
      "The serum bilirubin level is greater or equal to 3mg",
      "The spectrin level is less than 20 percent of normal membrane spectrin level",
      "Leg ulcers may be a complication"
    ],
    "answer": ["Leg ulcers may be a complication"],
    "explanation": "Severe Hereditary Spherocytosis can lead to various complications, including leg ulcers. Other features of the condition may include an increased risk of gallstones, anemia (hemoglobin level less than 6g/dl), elevated serum bilirubin levels, and reduced spectrin levels.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 8,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The following are laboratory findings in Hereditary Spherocytosis:",
    "options": [
      "The mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration is reduced",
      "The acid glycerol lysis time is reduced",
      "The glycerol unconjugated bilirubin is increased",
      "The reticulocyte count is reduced",
      "The serum lactate dehydrogenase level is elevated"
    ],
    "answer": ["The serum lactate dehydrogenase level is elevated"],
    "explanation": "Laboratory findings in Hereditary Spherocytosis often include an elevated serum lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) level, indicating ongoing hemolysis. Other common findings may include a reduced mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration, increased unconjugated bilirubin, and a high reticulocyte count.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 9,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Hereditary Elliptocytosis",
    "options": [
      "Severe disorder than hereditary elliptocytosis",
      "Basic defect is in Spectrin",
      "Majority of patients are symptomatic",
      "Majority of patients require therapy",
      "All of the above are correct"
    ],
    "answer": ["All of the above are correct"],
    "explanation": "Hereditary Elliptocytosis is a group of disorders characterized by elliptical-shaped red blood cells. It can vary in severity, with some patients being symptomatic and requiring therapy, while others may have milder forms. The basic defect in Hereditary Elliptocytosis often involves abnormalities in spectrin.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 10,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Bone marrow failure can be classified into",
    "options": [
      "Acquired marrow failure syndrome",
      "Idiopathic acquired AA",
      "Environmental",
      "Iatrogenic",
      "All of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["All of the above"],
    "explanation": "Bone marrow failure can be classified into various categories, including acquired marrow failure syndrome, idiopathic acquired aplastic anemia (AA), environmental causes, and iatrogenic factors. All of these can contribute to bone marrow failure.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 11,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Diagnosis of very severe aplastic anemia is characterized by",
    "options": [
      "Bone marrow hypercellularity >25%",
      "Absolute neutrophil count of <0.2 10^9/L",
      "Absolute reticulocyte count <10^9/1",
      "Absolute neutrophil count <0.5 100/1",
      "Platelet count <20 * 10^9/l"
    ],
    "answer": ["Absolute neutrophil count of <0.2 10^9/L"],
    "explanation": "Diagnosis of very severe aplastic anemia is characterized by bone marrow hypercellularity, where the bone marrow contains a higher-than-normal number of cells. This is often seen in the early stages of the disease.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 12,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Acquired immune hemolytic anemia",
    "options": [
      "Mediated by autoantibodies",
      "Classified into warm type at 37°C",
      "Classified into cold type at 4°C",
      "Cryopathic HAs autoAbs bind to RBCs at temps <37°C /4°C",
      "Mixed AHA does not exist"
    ],
    "answer": ["Cryopathic HAs autoAbs bind to RBCs at temps <37°C /4°C"],
    "explanation": "1. AIHA are mediated by autoantibodies production by the body against its own RCs \n2. classified by the temp at which autoAbs bind optimally to RBCs.  \n3. Majority of cases (80% to 90%) are mediated by antibodies that bind to RBCs at 37°C (warm type); \n4. while Cryopathic HAs, the autoAbs bind to RBCs at temps < 37°C/4°C (cold type). \n5.  Some patients exhibit both warm & cold reactive autoAbs (IgG & IgM) & are classified as mixed AHA. \n6. Hemolysis in mixed type is more severe AIHA due to IgA antibodies is rare.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 13,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Warm AIHA",
    "options": [
      "Red Cells are coated with IgM isotype alone",
      "Red Cells are coated with IgG isotype",
      "RBCs coated membrane lost can become spherical and is prematurely destroyed in the spleen",
      "Do not cause direct agglutination",
      "All of the above are correct"
    ],
    "answer": ["Do not cause direct agglutination"],
    "explanation": "About Warm autoimmune hemolytic anemia (AIHA) \n1. RCs are coated with Ig, usually IgG isotype alone/ complement (C3d), and are taken up by RE macrophages which have receptors for Ig Fc fragment. \n2. Part of the coated membrane is lost so the cell becomes spherical to maintain the same volume and is prematurely destroyed in spleen. \n3. Pathophysiology-Warm- reacting IgG antibodies bind optimally to antigens on RBCs at 37°C and may or may not fix complement, but they typically do not cause direct agglutination.\n4. Enhanced destruction of antibody- coated RBCs is mediated by Fc receptor– expressing macrophages. \n5. Partial phagocytosis results in the formation of spherocytes that may circulate for a time, become entrapped in the spleen, resulting in enhanced RBC destruction.\n\n SUMMARY\n1. Red cells are coated with IgG isotype alone \n2. Part(not all) of Red cells membrane lost can become spherical and is prematurely destroyed in the spleen\n3. Warm Acquired hemolytic aneamia typically do not cause direct agglutination",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 14,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The following are correctly matched",
    "options": [
      "Evans syndrome and ITP",
      "TIP and IIP",
      "Cold AIHA and Evans Syndrome",
      "Warm AIHA and IIP in Evans Syndrome",
      "None of the above is correct"
    ],
    "answer": ["Warm AIHA and IIP in Evans Syndrome"],
    "explanation": "None of the provided options correctly match the given conditions. It's important to understand the specific conditions and their associations correctly.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 15,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Laboratory findings in Warm AIHA are",
    "options": [
      "Typical of extravascular HA",
      "Reticulocytopenia may initially be present",
      "Marked elevations in MCV and MCHC",
      "PBF may show normocytic or macrocytic cells",
      "DAT is usually negative"
    ],
    "answer": ["DAT is usually negative"],
    "explanation": "Direct antiglobulin test (DAT) is typically negative in warm autoimmune hemolytic anemia (AIHA). Other laboratory findings may include reticulocytosis, normocytic or macrocytic red blood cells on peripheral blood film (PBF), and elevated levels of mean corpuscular volume (MCV) and mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC).",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 16,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Treatment options to decrease production of autoantibodies",
    "options": [
      "Prednisolone 60 mg/day starting dose",
      "Splenectomy may be of value in those who fail to respond",
      "Immunosuppression therapy",
      "Removal of the underlying cause not necessary",
      "Rituximab therapy can be used"
    ],
    "answer": ["Rituximab therapy can be used"],
    "explanation": "Rituximab, a monoclonal antibody, can be used in the treatment of autoimmune hemolytic anemia (AIHA) to decrease the production of autoantibodies. Other options such as prednisolone, splenectomy, and immunosuppression therapy may also be considered based on the patient's condition.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 17,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The following are not correct",
    "options": [
      "Antibody in cold AIHA syndrome is directed against 'I' antigen on RBC surface",
      "Antibody in mononucleosis is anti-i",
      "I antigens or i antigens bind below body temperature",
      "Donath-Landsteiner autoAb is seen in paroxysmal cold hemoglobinuria (PCH)",
      "PCH autoantibodies bind to antigens in the P blood group system"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "PCH autoantibodies bind to antigens in the P blood group system"
    ],
    "explanation": "Paroxysmal cold hemoglobinuria (PCH) autoantibodies bind to antigens in the P blood group system. The other provided options may have inaccuracies or incomplete information related to antibody specificity and temperature sensitivity in different conditions.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 18,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria",
    "options": [
      "Inherited clonal disorder HSCs",
      "Mutation of glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI) anchor occurs",
      "Deficiency or absence of phosphatidylinositol glycan class A gene (PIGA)",
      "CD55 and CD59 are found to be present only on red cells",
      "None of the above is correct"
    ],
    "answer": ["None of the above is correct"],
    "explanation": "None of the provided options accurately describes Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH). PNH is an acquired clonal disorder of hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) characterized by a mutation in the PIGA gene, leading to a deficiency of glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI)-anchored proteins. CD55 and CD59 are indeed found on red cells, but the options do not fully capture the complexity of PNH.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 19,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Definitive laboratory diagnosis for PNH",
    "options": [
      "Ham test",
      "Acidified serum lysis",
      "Sucrose hemolysis test",
      "Flow cytometry which shows loss of the GPI-linked proteins, CD55 and CD59",
      "Bone marrow examination reveals erythroid hyperplasia"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "Flow cytometry which shows loss of the GPI-linked proteins, CD55 and CD59"
    ],
    "explanation": "The definitive laboratory diagnosis for Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH) is typically achieved through flow cytometry, which can show the loss of glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI)-linked proteins such as CD55 and CD59 on the surface of blood cells. Other tests like the Ham test and acidified serum lysis can support the diagnosis.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 20,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Definitive treatment of PNH",
    "options": [
      "Iron and Folate supplementation",
      "Long-term anticoagulation with warfarin",
      "Rituximab",
      "Eculizumab, a humanized antibody against complement C5",
      "Allogeneic HSC transplantation"
    ],
    "answer": ["Allogeneic HSC transplantation"],
    "explanation": "The definitive treatment of Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH) often involves allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell (HSC) transplantation. Other treatment approaches may include Eculizumab, which targets complement C5, and supportive care such as iron and folate supplementation, but allogeneic HSC transplantation can potentially cure the condition.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 21,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Concerning Rh blood group system",
    "options": [
      "Second most important in blood transfusion",
      "4th blood group system to be discovered",
      "Complete Rh system of antigens are labeled as D, d, C, c, E, and e",
      "D is the most immunogenic, followed by C and E",
      "Routine donor and patient typing includes tests only for D"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "Complete Rh system of antigens are labeled as D, d, C, c, E, and e"
    ],
    "explanation": "Routine donor and patient typing for the Rh blood group system typically includes tests only for the presence or absence of the D antigen (Rh factor). While the other options provide information about the Rh system, the routine testing primarily focuses on the D antigen due to its clinical significance in blood transfusions.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 22,
    "question": "This is correct about sickle cell anaemia",
    "options": [
      "Absence of genes coding for B-chain",
      "The two B-chains are present but the amino acids components are reduced in number",
      "Excess of a-chains in comparison to B-chains",
      "There is valine replacing glutamic acid at position 6 in one B-chain and absence of a second B-chain",
      "It is the first and most studied inherited disorders in history"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "There is valine replacing glutamic acid at position 6 in one B-chain and absence of a second B-chain"
    ],
    "explanation": "Sickle cell anemia is caused by a point mutation in the beta-globin chain of hemoglobin. Specifically, there is a substitution of valine for glutamic acid at position 6 in one of the beta chains, leading to the characteristic sickle shape of red blood cells. The other options are incorrect."
  },

  {
    "id": 23,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "These are various hemoglobin types except",
    "options": [
      "Hb - α2μ2",
      "Hb - ζ2δ2",
      "Hb - ζ2ε2",
      "Hb - α2γ2",
      "Hb - α2β2"
    ],
    "answer": ["Hb - α2μ2"],
    "explanation": "Hemoglobin (Hb) exists in various forms, but Hb - α2γ2 is not one of them. Common types include HbA (α2β2), HbF (α2γ2), and others with different combinations of globin chains.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 24,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "One of the following will impede O₂ delivery to tissues in SCD",
    "options": [
      "Raised 2,3 DPG",
      "Acidosis",
      "Raised CO₂",
      "Hypoxia",
      "O₂ therapy"
    ],
    "answer": ["O₂ therapy"],
    "explanation": "Oxygen (O₂) therapy can actually worsen the condition in sickle cell disease (SCD) by reducing the sickling of red blood cells. This can impede O₂ delivery to tissues. Other factors listed can promote sickling and vaso-occlusive crises.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 25,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a sickle cell disease?",
    "options": ["HbSS", "HbSC", "HbSA", "HbSßThal", "HbS HPFH"],
    "answer": ["HbSA"],
    "explanation": "Hemoglobin S (HbS) is associated with sickle cell disease. HbSS, HbSC, HbSßThal, and HbS HPFH are various forms of sickle cell disease, while HbSA is not a sickle cell disease.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 26,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Which one of the following is least likely to precipitate vaso-occlusive crisis?",
    "options": [
      "Excessive sweating",
      "Acidosis",
      "Malaria infestation",
      "Persistently raised ambient temperature",
      "Passing the pathology examination"
    ],
    "answer": ["Passing the pathology examination"],
    "explanation": "Passing a pathology examination is not a known factor that precipitates vaso-occlusive crisis in sickle cell disease. The other options, such as excessive sweating, acidosis, malaria infestation, and raised ambient temperature, are more likely to contribute to vaso-occlusive crises.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 27,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "All of the following tests are useful in the diagnosis of unstable hemoglobins:",
    "options": [
      "Heinz body test",
      "Coombs test",
      "Hemoglobin electrophoresis",
      "Measuring the change of absorbance at a specific wavelength",
      "Hemoglobin stability test"
    ],
    "answer": ["Coombs test"],
    "explanation": "The Heinz body test is one of the tests used in the diagnosis of unstable hemoglobins. Unstable hemoglobins can lead to the formation of Heinz bodies, which can be detected using this test. Other tests listed are not specific for unstable hemoglobins.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 28,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Most iron in humans is found in:",
    "options": [
      "Hemoglobin",
      "Myoglobin",
      "Storage iron",
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Ferritin"
    ],
    "answer": ["Hemoglobin"],
    "explanation": "The majority of iron in humans is found in hemoglobin. Hemoglobin is the iron-containing protein in red blood cells that binds and transports oxygen throughout the body. While iron is also found in other forms, such as myoglobin and ferritin, the largest portion is in hemoglobin.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 29,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Findings in iron deficiency anemia include the following except",
    "options": [
      "Leptocytes",
      "Neutrophil hypersegmentation",
      "Target cells",
      "Microcytosis",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["None of the above"],
    "explanation": "Neutrophil hypersegmentation is not typically associated with iron deficiency anemia. However, other findings such as microcytosis, target cells, and the presence of leptocytes (target cells) can be seen in iron deficiency anemia.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Iron Deficiency Anemia", "Hypochromic anaemias"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 30,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The approximate iron content of three units of packed red cells for transfusion is:",
    "options": [
      "100mg of iron",
      "200mg of iron",
      "750mg of iron",
      "400mg of iron",
      "500mg of iron"
    ],
    "answer": ["750mg of iron"],
    "explanation": "The approximate iron content of three units of packed red cells for transfusion is about 750mg of iron. This iron can contribute to increasing the iron levels in the recipient's body.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 31,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Iron deficiency anemia is associated with which laboratory parameter:",
    "options": [
      "Elevated lactate dehydrogenase level",
      "Reduced serum calcium",
      "Elevated beta-2 microglobulin",
      "Elevated serum transferrin receptor level",
      "Reduced serum immunoglobulin"
    ],
    "answer": ["Elevated serum transferrin receptor level"],
    "explanation": "One of the laboratory parameters associated with iron deficiency anemia is an elevated serum transferrin receptor level. This can indicate the body's increased demand for iron due to iron deficiency.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Iron Deficiency Anemia", "Hypochromic anaemias"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 32,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Lab findings in Iron deficiency anemia include:",
    "options": [
      "Elevated total iron binding capacity",
      "Reduced free erythrocyte protoporphyrin",
      "Micronormoblast in the blood film",
      "Presence of dying cells in the blood film",
      "Elevated serum ferritin level"
    ],
    "answer": ["Elevated total iron binding capacity"],
    "explanation": "One of the laboratory findings in iron deficiency anemia is an elevated total iron binding capacity (TIBC). TIBC measures the body's capacity to bind iron with transferrin, and it increases in response to iron deficiency.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Iron Deficiency Anemia", "Hypochromic anaemias"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 33,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The major function of hepcidin is:",
    "options": [
      "Promote iron absorption in high plasma concentration",
      "Degrade ferroportin",
      "Disintegrate mitochondria",
      "Inhibit divalent metal transporter (DMT)",
      "Facilitate delivery to the fetus"
    ],
    "answer": ["Degrade ferroportin"],
    "explanation": "The major function of hepcidin is to degrade ferroportin, a protein that exports iron from cells into the bloodstream. By degrading ferroportin, hepcidin reduces iron release from cells and helps regulate iron homeostasis in the body.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 34,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The best method to assess iron in the plasma is measuring:",
    "options": [
      "Ferritin",
      "Haemosiderin",
      "Haptoglobin",
      "Ferroportin",
      "Hemoglobin"
    ],
    "answer": ["Ferritin"],
    "explanation": "The best method to assess iron levels in the plasma is by measuring ferritin levels. Ferritin is a protein that stores iron in a non-toxic form, and its concentration in the blood reflects the body's iron stores.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 35,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Excess bone marrow iron may be found in all but one of the following:",
    "options": [
      "Hereditary hemochromatosis",
      "Sideroblastic anemia",
      "Aplastic anemia",
      "Usually well Sickle cell anemia patients",
      "Thalassemia"
    ],
    "answer": ["Aplastic anemia"],
    "explanation": "Excess bone marrow iron is not typically found in aplastic anemia. It can be present in conditions like hereditary hemochromatosis, sideroblastic anemia, thalassemia, and in some well-managed sickle cell anemia patients.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 36,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Evidence of immune hemolytic anemia includes all except:",
    "options": [
      "Jaundice",
      "Reticulocytopenia",
      "Microspherocytosis",
      "Bone marrow erythroid hyperplasia",
      "Increased indirect bilirubin"
    ],
    "answer": ["Reticulocytopenia"],
    "explanation": "Microspherocytosis is not typically associated with immune hemolytic anemia. However, other evidence includes jaundice, reticulocytopenia, bone marrow erythroid hyperplasia, and increased indirect bilirubin.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 37,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Hemolytic anemia may be seen in the following condition except:",
    "options": [
      "Malaria infestation",
      "Clostridia infection",
      "Disseminated intravascular coagulopathy",
      "Burns",
      "Bleeding in a road transport accident victim"
    ],
    "answer": ["Bleeding in a road transport accident victim"],
    "explanation": "Disseminated intravascular coagulopathy (DIC) typically leads to the consumption of clotting factors and platelets, but it is not directly associated with hemolytic anemia. Hemolytic anemia can occur in conditions like malaria, clostridia infection, burns, and bleeding injuries.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 38,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "One of the following is unlikely to cause immune hemolytic anemia:",
    "options": [
      "Allograft such as stem cell transplant",
      "Presence of Cold antibody",
      "Septicemia",
      "Hemolytic transfusion reactions",
      "Hemolytic disease of the newborn"
    ],
    "answer": ["Septicemia"],
    "explanation": "Allografts like stem cell transplants are not typically associated with causing immune hemolytic anemia. However, the presence of cold antibodies, septicemia, hemolytic transfusion reactions, and hemolytic disease of the newborn can lead to immune hemolytic anemia.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 39,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Features of intravascular hemolysis include all except:",
    "options": [
      "Acute oliguric renal failure",
      "Absence of haptoglobin",
      "Reticulocytopenia",
      "Hemoglobinemia",
      "Coke-colored urine"
    ],
    "answer": ["Reticulocytopenia"],
    "explanation": "Intravascular hemolysis typically involves the destruction of red blood cells within the bloodstream. While it can lead to acute oliguric renal failure, absence of haptoglobin, hemoglobinemia, and coke-colored urine, it is not associated with reticulocytopenia.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 40,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The pathophysiology of megaloblastic anemia is:",
    "options": [
      "Defective RNA synthesis and abnormal cytoplasm maturation",
      "Defective DNA synthesis and abnormal nuclear maturation",
      "Defective RNA synthesis and abnormal nuclear maturation",
      "Defective DNA synthesis and abnormal cytoplasm maturation",
      "Defective RNA and DNA synthesis"
    ],
    "answer": ["Defective DNA synthesis and abnormal nuclear maturation"],
    "explanation": "The pathophysiology of megaloblastic anemia involves defective DNA synthesis and abnormal nuclear maturation. This leads to the production of large, immature red blood cells. It is not primarily related to RNA synthesis or cytoplasm maturation.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 41,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Features of megaloblastic anemia include the following except",
    "options": [
      "Macrocytosis",
      "Pancytopenia",
      "Multinucleated neutrophils",
      "Giant metamyelocytes",
      "Erythroid hyperplasia"
    ],
    "answer": ["Multinucleated neutrophils"],
    "explanation": "Megaloblastic anemia is characterized by macrocytosis, pancytopenia, multinucleated neutrophils, and giant metamyelocytes. However, it typically presents with ineffective erythropoiesis rather than erythroid hyperplasia.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 42,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Megaloblastic anemia is associated with:",
    "options": [
      "Ineffective erythropoiesis and increased reticulocytes",
      "Ineffective erythropoiesis and decreased reticulocytes",
      "Ineffective erythropoiesis and decreased LDH",
      "Ineffective erythropoiesis and decreased erythropoiesis",
      "Effective erythropoiesis and reticulocytosis"
    ],
    "answer": ["Ineffective erythropoiesis and decreased reticulocytes"],
    "explanation": "Megaloblastic anemia is characterized by ineffective erythropoiesis and increased reticulocytes in response to the destruction of large, immature red blood cells. It is not associated with effective erythropoiesis or decreased reticulocytes.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 43,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Rh-negative mothers may not have been sensitized to Rh-positive blood following:",
    "options": [
      "A second-trimester abortion",
      "A childhood blood transfusion",
      "Being an Rh-negative child of an Rh-positive mother",
      "A previous pregnancy with an Rh-negative baby",
      "Antepartum hemorrhage with an Rh D-negative fetus"
    ],
    "answer": ["Being an Rh-negative child of an Rh-positive mother"],
    "explanation": "Rh-negative mothers may not have been sensitized to Rh-positive blood following a previous pregnancy with an Rh-negative baby because sensitization typically occurs when an Rh-negative mother is exposed to Rh-positive fetal blood during pregnancy or delivery. The other options can lead to sensitization.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 44,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Concerning reticulocyte stain, which is incorrect",
    "options": [
      "It includes brilliant Cresyl blue and New methylene blue dyes",
      "It is useful to classify anemia",
      "It is useful in investigating alpha-thalassemia",
      "It can detect Heinz bodies",
      "It is a Romanovsky stain"
    ],
    "answer": ["It is a Romanovsky stain"],
    "explanation": "A reticulocyte stain, which includes dyes like brilliant Cresyl blue and New methylene blue, is useful for classifying anemia and investigating conditions like alpha-thalassemia. However, it is not typically used to detect Heinz bodies, which are better visualized with supravital stains.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 45,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Prussian blue stain is applied in the diagnosis of the following except",
    "options": [
      "Sideroblastic anemia",
      "Myelodysplastic syndrome",
      "Iron deficiency anemia",
      "Hemochromatosis",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["None of the above"],
    "explanation": "Prussian blue stain is used in the diagnosis of sideroblastic anemia, myelodysplastic syndrome, iron deficiency anemia, and hemochromatosis. Therefore, the correct answer is 'None of the above.'",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Iron Deficiency Anemia", "Hypochromic anaemias"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 46,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The reticulocyte count of an 18-year-old with anemia (PCV 20%) was 10%. Given that the maturation factor for the degree of anemia is 2 and the expected PCV is 40%, estimate the reticulocyte production index.",
    "options": ["5", "4", "3", "2.5", "1"],
    "answer": ["2.5"],
    "explanation": "The reticulocyte production index (RPI) can be estimated by dividing the observed reticulocyte count by the expected reticulocyte count. In this case, RPI = (10 / 2) = 5, which indicates a moderately increased reticulocyte production.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 47,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Possible differential diagnosis of an 18-year-old patient with anemia (PCV 20%) whose reticulocyte count was 10%.",
    "options": [
      "Megaloblastic anemia",
      "Aplastic anemia",
      "Iron deficiency anemia on therapy",
      "Mixed deficiency anemia",
      "Anemia due to renal failure"
    ],
    "answer": ["Iron deficiency anemia on therapy"],
    "explanation": "An 18-year-old patient with anemia (PCV 20%) and a reticulocyte count of 10% may have anemia due to renal failure. Other possible differential diagnoses like megaloblastic anemia, aplastic anemia, iron deficiency anemia on therapy, and mixed deficiency anemia should be considered based on clinical findings and further tests.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Iron Deficiency Anemia", "Hypochromic anaemias"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 48,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "The most common RBC enzyme defect of the glycolytic pathway is:",
    "options": [
      "Glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency",
      "Pyruvate kinase",
      "Glutathione reductase deficiency",
      "Hexose kinase deficiency",
      "Glucokinase deficiency"
    ],
    "answer": ["Pyruvate kinase"],
    "explanation": "The most common RBC enzyme defect of the glycolytic pathway is pyruvate kinase deficiency. It leads to hemolytic anemia due to the inability of RBCs to maintain their shape and integrity.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 49,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Concerning G6PD deficiency",
    "options": [
      "Is the commonest RBC enzyme defect",
      "It is an autosomal recessive disease",
      "Occurs in males only",
      "Causes extravascular hemolysis",
      "Splenectomy is beneficial"
    ],
    "answer": ["Is the commonest RBC enzyme defect"],
    "explanation": "Splenectomy can be beneficial in cases of G6PD deficiency because it removes a site of hemolysis, which can help improve hemoglobin levels and reduce hemolysis. However, it's important to consider the risks and benefits of splenectomy on a case-by-case basis.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 50,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Concerning Pyruvate Kinase deficiency",
    "options": [
      "Anemia symptoms are commensurate with the degree of anemia",
      "Is an autosomal dominant disease",
      "Causes intravascular hemolysis",
      "Oxygen dissociation curve shifts to the right",
      "Iron deficiency is a common finding"
    ],
    "answer": ["Oxygen dissociation curve shifts to the right"],
    "explanation": "Pyruvate Kinase deficiency can cause a variable degree of anemia, and the severity of symptoms is commensurate with the degree of anemia. It is not an autosomal dominant disease, and it does not cause intravascular hemolysis. The oxygen dissociation curve may shift to the left, and iron deficiency is not a common finding in this condition.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 52,
    "questionType": "objective",
    "question": "Hemolytic Disease of the Newborn",
    "options": [
      "Rh incompatibility is the most common cause of HDN is",
      "O mother with ABO incompatible infant",
      "Mother with Rh negative blood is pregnant with an Rh positive fetus",
      "Ex a mother with type O blood with an A or B infant"
    ],
    "answer": ["Ex a mother with type O blood with an A or B infant"],
    "explanation": "Hemolytic Disease of the Newborn (HDN) often occurs when a Rh-negative mother is pregnant with an Rh-positive fetus. This can lead to Rh incompatibility, with the mother producing antibodies against the Rh antigen of the fetus, which can cause hemolysis in the newborn.",
    "searchTags": [],
    "sources": ["2021 1st test"],
    "topics": ["Hematology"],
    "course": "Pathology",
    "subcourse": "Hematology",
    "numberofAttempt": 0,
    "averageUnderstanding": 0.0,
    "previous10AttemptQuestionscore": [],
    "averageUnderstandingRatePer10": [],
    "iscompleted": false,
    "averagerating": 0,
    "variationgiven": 0
  }
]
